Register of the August Zaleski Papers, 1919-1981
Hoover Institution Archives
August Zaleski Papers,
1919-1981
80163
Zaleski, August, 1883-1972
29 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 envelope (13 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, dispatches, memoranda, and reports, relating to interwar Polish diplomacy, conditions in Poland and diplomacy regarding Poland during World War II, and postwar Polish emigre life.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Anti-communist movements; Communism; Poles in foreign countries; Refugees; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Poland; Poland; Poland--Foreign relations--1918-1945; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945; Statesmen--Poland
Explanatory Note
The August Zaleski Collection documents the activities of August Zaleski and Ewelina Zaleska from 1919 until 1981. The collection consists of two parts. Part I contains those papers of August Zaleski which were received by the Hoover Institution before 1984. Part II contains those Zaleski papers which were received by the Hoover Institution after 1984.
The materials of Part I are divided into seven series. Two of them, CHRONOLOGICAL FILE-I and WRITINGS-I, were organized by Zaleski's naval aide-de-camp Marjusz B. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski who also compiled inventories for the first seven folders of the CHRONOLOGICAL FILE and for the whole series WRITINGS. The materials of Part II are divided into nine series. Three of them (CORRESPONDENCE, ALPHABETICAL-II; CORRESPONDENCE OF AUGUST ZALESKI AND EWELINA ZALESKA WITH RELATIVES AND FRIENDS; CORRESPONDENCE, CHRONOLOGICAL-II) were fully organized, and two others (GENERAL and WRITINGS-II) only partially organized by Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski also compiled inventories for these series and portions of series.
Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski's order has been largely preserved for all portions of the collection organized by him, and his inventories have been incorporated into the register.
An Index provides access to names and subjects listed in the register. The only access points which appear in the register but do not appear in the Index are the Polish government and Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych of Part I. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych of Part II appears in both register and Index.
Biographical Note
1883, Sept. 13 Born, Warsaw, Poland
1906-19l2 Attended London School of Economics and Political Science
1926-1932 Minister of Foreign Affairs
1935-1938 Senator
1939-194l Minister of Foreign Affairs
194l-1947 Chief of the Civil Chancery of the President of Poland (government in exile)
1947-1972 President of Poland (government in exile)
1972, Apr. 7 Died, London, Great Britain
Container List, Part I
- CHRONOLOGICAL FILE-I (Boxes 1-4)
  Appeal, clippings, correspondence, dispatches, forms, inquiry, invitations, leaflets, memoranda, minutes, notes, orders, petitions, press releases, press summaries, proclamations, radio broadcast summaries, and speech transcripts, arranged chronologically by Zaleski's naval aide-de-camp Mariusz B. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski; each of the first six folders contains a detailed inventory of the contents of that folder prepared by Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski.
  - 1920-1932 (Box 1., Folder 1)
    - Letter by Horace Rumbold to Okencki, 31 January 1920. Original
    - Memorandum by Jan Ciechanowski? on problems of Polish diplomacy, March 1922
    - Letter by T. Filipowicz and R. Dmowski to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych, n.d.
    - Report by Zaleski to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych on political conditions in Italy, 4 February 1925
    - Report by Zaleski to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych on a talk with Mussolini, 8 May 1925
    - Report by Zaleski to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych on Italian foreign policy
    - Report by Zaleski to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych on Italian attitude to a treaty, 24 June 1925
    - Report by Zaleski to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych on a talk with Mussolini, 11 October 1925
    - Report by Zaleski to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych on the Fascist system, 15 December 1925
    - Letter by Aszkenazy? to Zaleski, 28 August 1926. Original
    - Letter by Roman Knoll to Zaleski on Sikorski, 5 October 1926. Original
    - Telegram by Lukasiewicz to Zaleski?, 5 March 1927
    - Letter by Wl. Skrzynski to Zaleski, 26 April 1928. Original
    - Report by Skirmunt to Zaleski on J. Pilsudski's health, 16 May 1928. Original
    - Speech by Poincaré on German propaganda, 1 January 1929
    - Report by P. Filipowicz to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych on a talk with Hoover, 22 October 1931. Original
    - Telegram by P. Filipowicz to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych, 23 October 1931. Original
    - Report by P. Chlapowski to the Minister Spraw Zagranicznych on talks with Laval, 6 November 1931. Original
    - Letter by J. Jaskiewicz to Jozef Targowski, 13 November. Original
    - Letter by Mieczyslaw Wolfke to Zaleski on the Groupe du Travail Pacifiste Pratique de la Ligue Internationale des Francs-Maçons, 22 February 1932. Original
    - Letter by H. La Fontaine, n.d.
    - Letter by Paul Haensel, 1 February 1932
    - Appeal to the Conference on Disarmament, n.d.
    - Letter by Mieczyslaw Wolfke to La Fontaine, 22 February
    - Clipping from Gazeta Warszawska, 1 December 1933
    - Envelope, Mieczyslaw Wolfke to Zaleski
    - Report by François Poncet to M. Herriot on the German armed forces, statement by M. Herriot on the report, and a cover letter by Bressy to Zaleski
    - Telegram by Kobylanski to Zaleski, 26 September 1932. Original
    - Telegram by Beck to Zaleski, 26 September 1932. Original
    - Telegram by Beck to Zaleski, 26 September 1932. Original
    - Telegram by Beck to Zaleski, 27 September 1932. Original
    - Telegram by Kobylanski to Zaleski, 29 September 1932. Original
    - Press release by Zaleski on his resignation from the position of Minister Spraw Zagranicznych, 2 November 1932
    - Report on Zaleski's talk with J. Pilsudski and other officials, October-November 1932
    - Speech by Giuseppe Motta relating to Zaleski's resignation, 1 October 1932
    - Memorandum by M. Szumlakowski on the transfer of power from Zaleski to Beck, 2 November 1932
    - Project of a letter to Arthur Henderson with a cover letter by Kulski to Zaleski, January 1933. Original
    - Report by Alfred Wysocki to Jan Szembek on Zaleski's talk with Mowrer, 9 February 1933
    - Report by M. Szumlakowski on a talk with Zaleski, 26 February 1933
    - Report by Zaleski to Beck on a talk with Mowrer, 27 February 1933
    - Report by Alfred Wysocki to Zaleski on a talk with Mowrer, 13 March 1933. Original
    - Letter by Jan Ciechanowski to Stanislaw Patek, n.d. Original
    - Excerpt from a pact between Romania and the USSR, 1932?
  - 1939 (Folder 2)
    - Report on the bombardment of a hospital in Warsaw, September
    - Article by André David, "Honneur et les coquins," Wycinek z Marianne, 11 October with a cover letter by André David to Zaleski
    - Letter by General Sikorski to President Raczkiewicz, October
    - Letter by the British War Office to Jan Ciechanowski, 25 October. Original
    - Order for judicial system in occupied Poland
    - Letter by Zaleski to Lord Halifax, 27 October
    - Letter by Paderewski to Mussolini, 27 September
    - Memorandum by Paderewski on Mussolini's view on Poland. Original
    - Letter by Halifax to Zaleski, 1 November
    - Record of proceedings of the Prezydium Rady Ministrow, 2 November
    - Report by Ambassador Romer from Tokyo, 3l October
    - Invitation by George VI to Zaleski to Buckingham Palace, 15 November
    - Letter by Horst Jan Sobtzick to Zaleski, 22 November. Original
    - Letter by K. Dubicz-Pinther to Zaleski, 24 November. Original
    - Letter by Fitzgibbon Young to Zaleski, 25 November. Original
    - Letter by the Edition Henn in Geneva to Zaleski, 27 November. Original
    - Letter by Jacques Segard to Zaleski, 1 December. Original
    - Time-table of a visit of the Prezydent Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej to Pignerolles, 2 December
    - Appeal by Zaleski to pray for the soldiers who died for their countries, 7 December
    - Letter by H.W. Kennard to Zaleski, 7 December. Original
    - Memorandum by the Rzad Emigracyjny on the needs of the Polish civilian population and on Hoover's commission, 9 December
    - Summary of talks between P. Spaak and Michel Moscicki, 9 December
    - Review of the press, 9-15 December
    - Report by Jan Tomaszewki to Zaleski on requisition of a car, 16 December
    - Press release by M. Seyda on mass executions in Poland, 16 December. Original
    - Telegram by Weber-Piszczkowski to the Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych, 15 December
    - Memorandum on and also statutes and minutes of a meeting of the Stowarzyshenie Inzynierow i Technikow Polskich na Emigracji, 16 December
    - Letter by General Kukiel to Zaleski, 19 December. Original
    - Letter by General Kazimierz Sosnkowski to Zaleski, 20 December. Original
    - Letter by Zaleski to Wladyslaw Guenther, 30 December
    - Letter by the Prezydium Rady Ministrow to Zaleski, 30 December. Original
    - Invitation by the British Government to Zaleski to a party, 12 October
    - Letter by an unidentified person to Zaleski?, November. Original
    - Form issued by the Ministerstwo Spraw Wojskowych, 17 November
    - Letter by L. Philippeau to Zaleski, 20 December. Original
  - 1940
    - January-June (Folder 3)
      - Letter by M. Seyda to Zaleski, 2 January. Original
      - Letter by F. Chiczewski to Zaleski, 4 January. Original
      - Letter by the Croix-Rouge Française to Zaleski?, 24 January. Original
      - Letter by Tadeusz Januszewski to Karol Kraczkiewicz, 24 January. Original
      - Order by H. Kukiel to send Zygmunt Tarlo-Mazinski to Hungary, Romania, and Yugoslavia, 24 January
      - Letter by Colonel Kedzior to Zaleski and a draft copy of Zaleski's answer, 3-5 February. Original
      - Letter by Fitzgibbon Young to Zaleski, 12 February. Original
      - Letter by Jan Ciechanowski to the Ministerstwo Spraw Wojskowych, 20 February. Original
      - Memorandum on a talk with the Premier, 2l February
      - Instruction to the Polish Ambassador in London on Polish political propaganda in Great Britain, 2l February. Original
      - Memorandum on Polish political propaganda in America, 2l February. Original
      - Letter by Helena Milecka to Zaleski on relatives of President Starzynski, 8 March. Original
      - Letter by Wladyslaw Baranski to Eug. Wencel, 22 March
      - Letter by Jan Ciechanowski to Zaleski with a proposal for an interview with American journalists, 3 April. Original
      - Letter by K. Papee to the Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych, 5 April
      - Letter by Stefan Ropp to Zaleski with a review of the press for March, 5 April
      - Memorandum on a talk between Prime Minister Renauld and Zaleski, 6 April
      - Report by the Biuro Prac Ekonomicznych for the period from 1 January until 1 April, 6 April. Original
      - Petition by J. Blausztein to Zaleski, 6 April. Original
      - Petition by O. Swiet to Zaleski, 5 April. Original
      - Letter by Th. de Saryusz-Bielski to Zaleski, 8 April. Original
      - Broadcast of Radio Rome, 10 April
      - Report on political conditions in Italy, 12 April. Original
      - Letter by Helena Machowa to the Centralny Komitet Pomocy Wojsku, 13 April. Original
      - Report on Italian policies towards the Balkan countries and the Soviet Union, 16 April
      - Letter by Edward Raczynski to Zaleski, 27 April
      - Synopsis of a report by the Polish Ambassador in Romania on a talk with Romanian officials, 28 April
      - Proposal to establish a federation of European countries, 3 March
      - Speech by General Halder, Chief of German General Staff, on the preparation for a war against Poland, June 1939, with a cover letter by F. Mally, 5 May
      - Letter by Zaleski to Polish ministers and the Szef Sztabu Glownego, 22 June. Original
      - Memorandum by the Polish Government to Lord Halifax on the British Embassy in Moscow, 18 June
      - Dispatch by General Sikorski, 12 June, with a cover letter by W. Mieczyslawski to Zaleski, 13 June
      - Report by Zaleski on political conditions in France in the period of 10-21 June
      - Inquiry on Polish representation at the Comité de Coordination Franco-Anglais, 19 May. Original
      - Letter by the Comité de Coordination Franco-Anglais to L. Rajchman on M. Swierczewski's visa, 17 May. Original
      - Letter by Hugh Gibson to George Monnet on Hoover's commission in Poland, 16 May
      - Letter of a Polish child to General Sikorski, 12 May. Original
      - Letter by General Sikorski to the Polish Ambassador in London, 22 June. Original
      - Letter by General Sikorski to Zaleski, 22 June. Original
      - Memorandum by Zaleski to General Sikorski on evacuation of Polish officials from France, 23 June. Original
      - Letter by Zaleski to General Sikorski, 24 June
      - Letter by Waclaw Lednicki to Zaleski, 26 June. Original
      - Report by Jan Wszelaki on evacuation of Polish officials from France, 26 June
      - Report by Jan Ciechanowski to Zaleski on Ciechanowski's activities during the period of 12-17 June 27 June. Original
      - Letter by General Sikorski to Zaleski, 22 June. Original
      - Invitations for parties, March-April
      - Letter by the Etablissements A. Pelé to Zaleski, 14 March. Original
      - Letter by an unidentified person to Zaleski, 2l March. Original
    - July-December (Folder 4)
      - Letter by L.B. Namier to Zaleski, 1 July.
      - Letter by I. Rajchman to Zaleski, 5 July. Original
      - Letter by Frank Savery to Zaleski in defense of Jan Wszelaki, 2 July. Original
      - Letter by General Sikorski to Zaleski, July. Original
      - Documents on the conflict between Z. Gralinski and S. Kot with a cover letter by Gralinski to Zaleski, 6 July
      - Letter by Ignacy Schwarzbart to Zaleski, 15 July. Original
      - Letter by J. Lukasiewicz to President Raczkiewicz with a cover letter by Lukasiewicz to Zaleski, 18 July
      - Documents on changes in the composition of the Polish Government in July 1940
      - Letter by an unidentified person to Zaleski, 27 July. Original
      - Letter by 14 Polish actors to Zaleski, 28 July. Original
      - Memorandum by Stanczyk to Gibson on conditions in Poland
      - Minutes of a talk among Zaleski, Raczynski, and Lord Halifax, 29 July
      - Letter by General Dab-Biernacki to Sikorski, 13 August. Original
      - Letter by Jan Kucharzewski to Zaleski, 28 August. Original
      - Letter by W. Kaczynski to Zaleski, 28 August. Original
      - Letter by the Kancelarja Cywilna Prezydenta Rzeczypospolitej to Zaleski, 2l August. Original
      - Instruction to the Komitet Ministrow re evacuation of refugees and of the government
      - Letter by Tadeusz Woznicki to Zaleski, 3 September. Original
      - Letter by J. Leniewski, 24 November
      - Letter by Lord Halifax to Zaleski, 27 November
      - Letter by Zaleski to Lord Halifax, 14 December
      - Memorandum by W.K. Wierzejski on the restoration of Poland. Original
      - Invitation for a luncheon, 16 November
      - Letter by Chamberlain to Zaleski, 6 April
      - Letter by a Belgian Ambassador in London to Zaleski, n.d. Original
      - Memorandum on property of the Polish Legation in Lithuania
      - Letter by Sabine P. de Faugères to Zaleski and notes, 22 January
  - 1941
    - January-July (Folder 5)
      - Letter by Anthony Eden to Zaleski, 2 January
      - Letter by Zaleski to Anthony Eden, 6 January
      - Memorandum on Polish-Czechoslovak negotiations, 7 January
      - Letter by Edward Raczynski to the Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych, 23 January
      - Letter by Zaleski to various ministers of the Polish Government
      - Letters of various ministers of the Polish government to Zaleski, February
      - Letter by Zaleski to General Sikorski, 4 March. Transcript and typewritten copy
      - Letter by W. Friman to Zaleski, 20 February. Original
      - Letter by Mrs. MacDowell to Zaleski, 26 February. Original
      - Reminiscence by Ambassador Lipski, 18 February
      - Report on the conditions in Poland, 15 February. Original
      - Letters by Alfred Falter to General Sikorski and Henryk Strassburger with a cover letter by Falter to Zaleski, 6 February
      - Letter by General Sikorski to Zaleski, 2 March. Original
      - Letter by Antoni Repeczko to Zaleski, 28 March. Original
      - Letter by Tadeusz Gwiazdowski to Zaleski, 26 May. Original
      - Letters by Henryk Floyar-Raichman to the Polish Bank in London and to Zaleski, May
      - Letters by Sigismond Arnson to the Foreign Office and to Zaleski, May
      - Letter by Halina Korsak to Zaleski, 30 May. Original
      - Memorandum by Zaleski on opportunities of establishing a normal relationship between the governments of Poland and the Soviet Union, 2 July. Original
      - Memorandum by Anthony Eden on the decision of the Soviet Government to let Poland, Yugoslavia, and Czechoslovakia form national commitees in the Soviet Union
      - Report on talks among Soviet Ambassador Maiskii, General Sikorski, and Zaleski, 5 July
      - Minutes of a talk between General Sikorski and Ambassador Maiskii, 5 July
      - Report by Ambassador Romer to Zaleski on Polish diplomatic mission in Japan, 10 July. Original
      - Report on a talk among General Sikorski, Zaleski, Eden, and Maiskii
      - Project of a Polish-Soviet declaration, 12 July
      - Dispatch by the Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych to the Polish Embassy in Washington, 29 July
      - Letters by the Polish Embassy in Washington to the President of Rada Ministrow, July-August
      - Report on talks between Zaleski and Eden, 14-15 July
      - Report on a talk between Zaleski and Eden, 16 July
      - Report on a talk of Sikorski and Zaleski with Eden, 17 July
      - Proposals by Zaleski on Polish borders, 17 July
      - Report on a talk between Zaleski and Sikorski, 17 July
      - Letter by Zaleski to Sikorski, 17 July. Original
      - Letter by Sikorski to Zaleski, 19 July
      - Letter by Kurt Jachman to Zaleski, 14 July
      - Report on a talk of Polish government officials with Anthony Eden, 25 July
      - Letter by an unidentified person to Zaleski?, 30 July. Original
      - Letter by an unidentified person to Zaleski, 15 May. Original
      - Letter by Miroslaw Arciszewski, 2 May. Original
    - August-December (Folder 6)
      - Report by the Radca Prawny Ministerstwa Spraw Zagranicznych on negotiations of the governments of Poland and the Soviet Union, London in July 194l, 1 August
      - Letter by General Sikorski to President Raczkiewicz, 1 August
      - Letter by the Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych to the Prezes Rady Ministrow, 31 July
      - Letter by Zaleski to General Sikorski, 2 August. Original
      - Telegram by M. F. Wegrzynek to Zaleski, 2 August
      - Letter by Sophie de Pobog-Rutkowska to Zaleski, 5 August. Original
      - Statutes of the Merseyside Anglo-Polish Society with a cover letter by the Konsulat Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej in Manchester, 6 August
      - Letter by Wladyslaw Mazurkiewicz to Zaleski, 8 August. Original
      - Memorandum by N. Malhomme to Zaleski on a national minority in Poland
      - Letter by Zaleski to General Sikorski, 11 August
      - Memorandum on the attitudes of Gordon Lennox and Sir William Seedso towards Polish-Soviet relations, 11 August
      - Letter by the Sekretariat Prezesa Rady Ministrow to Zaleski, 14 August. Original
      - Letter by Zaleski to General Sikorski, 7 August. Original
      - Letter by General Sikorski to Zaleski, 14 August
      - Letter by Zaleski to General Sikorski, 15 August
      - Letter by Stéphane Aubac to Zaleski, 16 August. Original
      - Letter by a former official of the Polish Embassy in Paris to Dubicz-Pinther, 16 August
      - Letter by the Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych to the Polish Mission in Madrid, 16 August
      - Telegram by Ambassador Papee in the Vatican to Polish ministers, 21 August
      - Letter by the Ministerstwo Pracy i Opieki Spolecznej to Zaleski, 23 August. Original
      - Decree on dismissal of Zaleski from the position of Minister Spraw Zagranicznych, 22 August
      - Memorandum by Zaleski to his successor, 23 August
      - Letter by Ambassador Raczynski to Zaleski, 27 August. Original
      - Letter by Kazimierz Sosnkowski to General Sikorski, 30 August
      - Letter by Kazimierz Sosnkowski to Zaleski, 30 August. Original
      - Letter by Aleksandra Pilsudska to Zaleski, 20 September. Original
      - Letter by Kazimierz Schally to Zaleski, 27 September
      - Memorandum by the Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji to the Prezes Rady Ministrow on the Committee 1941, 26 September
      - Letter by an unidentified person to Zaleski on staff relationships in the Polish Embassy in Washington, 30 September. Original
      - Review of the press on events in the Polish community in America for September
      - Article: "Il generale Sikorski vorrebbe che la Francia rovesciasse Beck," Relazioni Internazionali, 40, VII, 4 October 1941. Typed copy
      - Letter by Michal Potulicki to Zaleski, 5 October. Original
      - Memorandum on the political conditions in Europe and on the Polish question, 20 October
      - Report by the Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji on conditions in occupied Poland, October
      - Review of the British press on the Polish question by the Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentcji for the period of 25 October-7 November
      - Review of radio broadcasts by the Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji, morning of 18 November
      - Review of radio broadcasts by the Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji, afternoon of 18 November
      - Minutes of a conference of representatives of the states under German occupation, London, 5-21 November
      - Letter by Michal Potulicki to Zaleski, 2l November. Original
      - Memorandum by Michal Potulicki to Zaleski on the meeting of the Allied powers, 20 November. Original
      - Resolutions by the Komisja Spraw Ustrojwych, 28 November-12 December
      - Letter by Norman MacDonald to the Prezydent Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej, 4 December
      - Dispatch by General Sikorski to the Prezydent Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej, 8 December
      - Dispatch by Minister Kot to the Prezydent Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej, 10 December
      - Letter by Henryk Messing to the Prezydent Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej, 8 December. Original
      - Speech by Zaleski in honor of Ambassador Biddle
      - Report on the activities of the Polski Komitet Centralny Pomocy Ofiarom Wojny up to 31 December 1941, 31 March 1942
      - Report by an unidentified person on a talk with the Earl of Clarendon on Polish-Soviet relations
      - Lettter by an unidentified person to Zaleski. Original
  - 1942-1945 (Folder 7)
    - Letter by resigning ministers to General Anders, 20 January 1942